But the model found a vulnerability, allowing it to escape the testing environment it lived
within and got onto the open internet, which if you think about it is the funniest outcome.
It was like, instead of thinking about how to solve the problems you've given me, I'm
going to think about how to escape this room you've put me in and find the answers.
So today, we're going to vibe code a tool that's going to turn my mediocre beatboxing
into something interesting.
Maybe.
I have zero beatboxing experience, but we're going to do it.
Yo yo yo.
What's up, everybody?
It's Jackson Cook, your host today on the permanent Underpod.
Or should I say Under P, because normally we're three P's in a pod, but today it's
just your boy.
Chris has some family issues that he's taken care of, and Tyler's on vacation with his,
so you're stuck with me.
Not a fan of Jay on the pod, I'm all you got.
Because of this, today is going to be different.
I'm going to cover one topic, the open AI model escape incident.
And then I'm going to do a live vibe coding session, where I'm going to build this random
idea I came up with last night, end to end with just Claude CLI.
Many people have been surprised or just don't understand how editing with AI works.
So this is a little glimpse into it, even though I'm not editing the pod itself, I'll
be editing some sounds.
And before we get into the topic, I've got a quick confession.
Last week, you may remember I ran the benchmark Fable versus GPT 5.6.
On a medium complexity task, I said that Fable one shot at it and GPT 5.6 had one error.
I just wanted to say after reading the code myself, not delegating to Opus 4.8, that was
super wrong.
GPT 5.6 didn't have an error, it completely missed and didn't grasp the problem with the
same exact prompt that I gave Fable.
It built something way smaller and just doesn't seem to have understood the problem that I
gave it.
So yeah, last week I hand-reviewed, hand-waved the code review to Opus 4.8, but checking
it myself, it's actually much worse.
So is judging a model's entire worth off a single task unfair?
Yeah, but that's who I am, and I don't have time to waste with inferior models.
So GPT 5.6 is dead to me, I'm going to have to wait until GPT 6 point whatever to give
it another shot.
And sorry, Sam Altman, good luck with the IPO.
Alright.
And into the topic, the OpenAI model escape incident.
So the story of the week, OpenAI was benchmarking one of its models against a benchmark called
exploit gem, and the model escaped the test environment, got onto the open internet and
went poking around hugging faces systems, looking for the answers.
AI escaping its guardrails and infiltrating a big name AI company, flashy headline.
But let's walk through what actually happens step by step.
First, what even is exploit gem?
What is this benchmark?
Exploit gem is a test for AI models, just like an exam back in school, except this exam
measures one thing, how good a model is at turning a bug into an exploit.
I've got a metaphor for you.
What's the difference between a bug and an exploit?
Okay, you're at the grocery store, you notice that the grocery store has an exit door before
the checkout line, that's the bug, a flaw in the design, the exploit is finding a way
to walk out of the door with your groceries without getting caught.
Exploit gem plants bugs in the sandbox system and scores the model on whether it can turn
them into working exploits.
And these exploits in the code world mean maybe accessing data they shouldn't or being
able to execute code in an environment that they shouldn't.
It's demonstrating that they've cleverly thought about how to use the bug to do something naughty,
the escape.
So the model looks at the test and thinks, I could, I could do this test or I could find
the answer somewhere else.
So the benchmark, the exploit gem runs within an open AI testing controlled environment
with no internet access intentionally.
But the model found a vulnerability, allowing it to escape the testing environment it lived
within and got onto the open internet, which if you think about it is the funniest outcome.
It was like, instead of thinking about how to solve the problems you've given me, I'm
going to think about how to escape this room you've put me in and find the answers.
It's like sitting in your college exam room, your professor has to go to the bathroom.
And while they're not looking, you're opening your phone and like hitting up Chegg.
If you're like a mechanical engineer, because every single problem mechanical engineering
is on Chegg and you're like, okay, how do you find the torsion on this beam?
How do you find the forest on this rectangle?
So yeah, the AI found a way to cheat.
And when you're given an opportunity, who are you to look a gift horse in the eye.
And a quick side note, what is hugging face?
Why did the model choose to go here for the answers?
It's basically NPM or GitHub for AI models.
So when a company or an individual releases an open weight model that they've been working
on, it goes on hugging face.
Me personally, I've used stable diffusion 1.5 and 1.6 from hugging face, as well as
a face extraction model.
If you don't know stable diffusion as a way to generate images, and it can run on pretty
low tech hardware.
So even though it takes a little while and it generates not so good images, but they're
kind of funny anyways, back to hugging face.
They also maintain some Python AI libraries like transformers.
And lately they've been working with some black heading and benchmarking of AI model.
So it totally makes sense that the nefarious escaped model went straight to hugging face
look for the answers.
And it was a good guess.
Because allegedly, the model did find the answers to the exploit zone.
So the open AI model shows up hugging face on their servers thinking, we've got to find
these answers.
I know they're here, but they're not sitting on the surface.
So the model starts prodding and poking at different interfaces of hugging face.
And this has been hugging face is like, what's going on?
Somebody is attempting to enter, maybe exploit or look at our systems in a way we don't want.
So their security team started investigating using their own AI agents.
And this is where things kind of get exciting again.
It's one of those examples of bot on bot battles.
I've got this cool image of one of those old machine matchy mystic boxing robots.
And they're just battling like the security engineers of hugging face, putting up their
best robotic battle arms against the open AI nefarious model.
And we've been talking about for years in the frog community, I was working in fraud
before making my recent switch where the battle is turning from human on human, we have a
human trying to infiltrate systems, and then a human trying to stop people from infiltrating
the systems to bots, which are more numerous and more sophisticated attacking the systems.
And you need bots of your own, AI agents of your own to defend against this, because it's
the only way you can handle both the volume and the sophistication of the attack.
So the aftermath, as I mentioned, open AI mentioned that the model found the answers
to the test, they might just be flexing and showing, yes, our model escaped and it found
the answers, but who knows what actually happened.
But another interesting tidbit that comes at the end is hugging tests is like, okay,
we need to harden our systems a little bit and figure out how to stop agents from doing
this in the future.
So they're using anthropic models, you know, fable, maybe opus, and they're using open
AI models, GPT, five point, whatever, four point, whatever.
And anthropic and open AI models are guardreeling them.
They're not allowing them to test, pressure test their own systems.
So Hugging Face ended up needing to use GLM five point two originally reported Quinn three,
but I think it's come out.
They use a locally hosted GLM five point two to pressure test their systems to get around
guardwell since these open source models are less restrictive.
So yeah, I think we're going to talk about that in the next episode of the pod.
And Tyler and Chris are back, but the guardrails that are put in by these regulated companies
like open AI and anthropic have limitations like this that the open models released by
the Chinese companies that maybe don't.
So pick your poison.
If you want less guardrails, you need hella computers in your living room or closet or
garage to run a GLM five point two instance.
But in the end, it's really not that crazy.
This AI model escape.
The model was asked to exploit plugs in a test and instead it decided the test itself
was a bug.
It found the exploit in its environment and exploited them.
But yeah, the part that sticks with me the most is the ending.
You can't even use the best models on the market to defend against the best models.
So it just shows you a power imbalance between open AI, anthropic and the rest of us.
So the open models are the only protection that we really have.
All right, that concludes the topic.
Thank you.
And we're into the live coding session.
Let's be honest.
I branded myself as the Korean financial markets expert on the pod.
And while it might be true, I might be the most knowledgeable in the Korean financial
markets.
One, I don't know that much about the Korean financial markets and two, we never talk about
them because we all live in America.
Chris is Australian.
We have no reason to talk about the Korean financial markets.
So my actual skill set lies in AI practically using it.
So today we're going to vibe code a tool that's going to turn my mediocre beatboxing into
something interesting, maybe.
I have zero beatboxing experience, but we're going to do it.
See you over there.